A Guide to the Mabel Harris Papers, 1888-1945
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Mabel Harris Papers, 1888-1945
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1945-5
There are c. 200 items in this collection.
This collection contains business, personal, and legal correspondence of the 1889 Normal Graduates of Virginia State University. Miss Harris taught in the public schools in Petersburg until her retirement.
These materials were collected by the late Luther Porter Jackson in 1945.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions to this collection.
Biographical/Historical Information
Mabel Harris was born in Petersburg, Virginia in 1867. Information about her early life is not well documented. She was at the Virginia Normal and Collegiate Institute (now Virginia State University) in 1886, taking a normal degree three years later. She began her career in the Petersburg Public School system in 1890. Miss Harris retired in 1931. She was very active in local church affairs and the Virginia State University Alumni Association. She was the first female to be appointed editor of the Alumni Journal for the University, in 1898.
Scope and Content Information
Most of the materials in this collection pertain to Miss Harris' uncle, the Reverend Mr. Henry Williams. There are a few items from friends, basically discussing personal business and/or inquiring as to her health and other activities. The materials are useful for local history, women's history and the history of education.
Organization
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Legal Documents
Series III. Financial
Series IV. Tax Recepits
Series V. Writing
Series VI. Photographs
Series VII. Printed Material
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence 1888-1945
  Letters and postcards, mostly personal, all incoming.
  Arranged chronologically, from 1888-1945.
  - General correspondence 1888-1894 (Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence 1900-1906 (Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence 1907-1908 (Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence 1908-1910 (Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence 1912-1928 (Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence 1944-1945 (Folder 6)
- Series II. Legal Documents 1889, 1895, 1896, 1899 (Folder 7)
  Teaching contracts for Petersburg Public Schools, 1880s-1890s
- Series III. Financial n.d. (Folder 8)
  This collection contains 3 documents: Savings Book for the Peoples Bank of Petersburg; an account of the holdings of the Old Dominion Investment Company; A true Reformer Insurance Policy.
- Series IV. Tax Receipts n.d. (Folder 9)
  City & state tax receipts
- Series V. Writings n.d. (Folder 9)
- Series VI. Photographs n.d. (Folder 11)
  There are 2 photographs in this collection, one sent from a member of the Tenth United States Calvary (Buffalo Soldiers), stationed in Cuba.
- Series VII. Printed n.d. (Folder 12)
  One hand bill for Camilla Williams